Nils Albin Nilsson

September 18, 2020

National Centre for Nuclear Research ul. Pasteura 7 02-093 Warsaw, Poland albin.nilsson@ncbj.gov.pl +48-660083924

Home address: ul. 2F Edinburgh Drive OX11 7LT Didcot, UK albin.nilsson@protonmail.ch

Profile

Highly analytical early-career researcher in physics with teaching experience. My main research interests are phenomenology of new physics in gravity and cosmology, in particular bridging theory and observations, along with early Universe physics and General Relativity.

Education

• Ph.D. in Physics

Warsaw, Poland

Lund, Sweden June 15, 2015

National Centre for Nuclear Research

September 14, 2020

- Title of thesis: Aspects of Lorentz and CPT Violation in Cosmology
- Supervisor: Mariusz P. Dąbrowski
- MSc. Engineering physics

Lund Institute of Technology

- Title of thesis: Astrophysical Probes of Models of Quantum Gravity

- Supervisor: John Ellis

Publications

Refereed Journal Articles

• N.A. Nilsson

Preferred-frame Effects, the H_0 tension, and Probes of Hořava-Lifshitz Gravity, Eur. Phys. J. Plus 135 (2020) 4, 361, I.F 2.612

• N.A.Nilsson, E.Czuchry

Hořava-Lifshitz Cosmology in Light of New Data Phys.Dark Univ. C23 (2019) 100253, I.F 6.509, Citations: 10

• N.A.Nilsson, M.Dąbrowski

Energy Scale of Lorentz Violation in Rainbow Gravity Phys.Dark Univ. 18 (2017) 115-122, I.F 5.425, Citations: 6

• M.Fairbairn, N.A.Nilsson, J.Ellis, J.Hinton, R.White The CTA Sensitivity to Lorentz-Violating Effects on the Gamma-Ray Horizon JCAP 1406 (2014) 005, I.F 5.81, Citations: 29

Articles in Preparation

- K.O'Neil Ault, Q.B.Bailey, N.A. Nilsson, Hamiltonian Formulation of the Standard-Model Extension Gravity Sector, arXiv:2009.00949, submitted to Phys.Rev.D.
- M.P. Dabrowski, N.A. Nilsson Antisymmetric Tensor Field Configurations in Cosmology

Conference Proceedings

• N.A.Nilsson, K.O'Neil Ault, Q.B.Bailey

A 3+1 Decomposition of the Minimal Standard-Model Extension Gravitational Sector

CPT and Lorentz Symmetry, pp. 198-200 (2020), Citations: 4

Other Publications

• N.A. Nilsson

Incentives, Rewards, and Recognition - What Really Motivates a Researcher? Essay published for the MDPI essay contest Judging Research - How Should Research and Researchers Be Evaluated and Rewarded? ISBN 978-3-03928-314-9

• N.A. Nilsson

Commodity or Public Property? Essay published for the MDPI essay contest The Global Benefits of Open Research ISBN 978-3-03897-009-5

Awards and Honours

- 2019: Winner of the MDPI English Writing Competition for the essay "Incentives, Rewards and Recognition What Really Motivates a Researcher?", 460 EUR
- 2019: NCBJ Award for Outstanding Achievements for PhD Students, 600 EUR
- 2018: NCBJ Award for Outstanding Achievements for PhD Students, 600 EUR

Grants

• 2018: PI and sole applicant for NCBJ Young Scientist Grant MNiSW 212737/E-78/M/2018, Title: Tensor Lorentz Violation in Cosmology with Antisymmetric Tensor Fields, 3300 EUR

Invited Talks

• "Aspects of Lorentz Violation in Gravity & Cosmology" Paris, France
Paris Observatory October 17, 2019

• "Successes and Problems of the ACDM Model" Prescott, USA Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University April 4, 2019

• "Quantum Gravity, Lorentz Violation, and Rainbows" Szczecin, Poland University of Szczecin

December 9, 2016

Physics Meetings

Oral Contribution

• "Ongoing Efforts to Constrain Lorentz Symmetry Violation in Gravity" Krakow, Poland (online)

Spring Workshop on Gravity and Cosmology

May 26, 2020

• "Antisymmetric Tensors in Friedmann Cosmology" 6th Conference of the Polish Society of Relativity Szczecin, Poland September 23-26, 2019

• "A 3+1 Decomposition of the Minimal SME Gravitational Sec Eighth Meeting on CPT and Lorentz Symmetry	ctor" Bloomington, USA May 12-16, 2019
• "Hořava-Lifshitz Gravity in Light of New Data" Testing Gravity 2019	Vancouver, Canada January 23-26, 2019
• "Cosmological Evolution in Lorentz Breaking Gravity" IUCSS Summer School on the Lorentz and CPT violating SME	Bloomington, USA June 15-23, 2018
• "Toward Quantum Gravity Phenomenology" Singularities in General Relativity and their Quantum Fate	Warsaw, Poland May 21-25, 2018
• "Probing Hořava-Lifshitz Cosmology" SpringCosmo18	Zeuten, Germany May 19-21, 2018
 "Searching for Lorentz Invariance Violation in Theories with Modified Dispersion Relations" 3rd Azores School on Observational Cosmology 	Azores, Portugal August 27-September 2, 2017
• Theories with Modified Dispersion Relations "SpringCosmofun 17"	Międzyzdroje, Poland May 19-21, 2017
Meetings Organised	
• Sixth Conference of the Polish Society of Relativity	Szczecin, Poland September 23-26, 2019
	Wangara Daland
• Singularities in General Relativity and their Quantum Fate	Warsaw, Poland May 21-25, 2018
Singularities in General Relativity and their Quantum Fate Research Visits	
Research Visits • Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University	May 21-25, 2018 Prescott, USA
Research Visits • Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University Visiting Professor Quentin G. Bailey • Lagrange Institute	May 21-25, 2018 Prescott, USA January 25-31, 2020 Paris, France
 Research Visits Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University Visiting Professor Quentin G. Bailey Lagrange Institute Visiting Professor Patrick Peter Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University 	Prescott, USA January 25-31, 2020 Paris, France October 21-25, 2019 Prescott, USA
 Research Visits Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University Visiting Professor Quentin G. Bailey Lagrange Institute Visiting Professor Patrick Peter Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University Visiting Professor Quentin G. Bailey 	Prescott, USA January 25-31, 2020 Paris, France October 21-25, 2019 Prescott, USA April 3-18, 2019
Research Visits • Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University Visiting Professor Quentin G. Bailey • Lagrange Institute Visiting Professor Patrick Peter • Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University Visiting Professor Quentin G. Bailey Departmental Talks • "Lorentz Violation and Extra Dimensions with Gravity Probe	Prescott, USA January 25-31, 2020 Paris, France October 21-25, 2019 Prescott, USA April 3-18, 2019 B" Warsaw, Poland November 5, 2018
Research Visits • Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University Visiting Professor Quentin G. Bailey • Lagrange Institute Visiting Professor Patrick Peter • Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University Visiting Professor Quentin G. Bailey Departmental Talks • "Lorentz Violation and Extra Dimensions with Gravity Probe National Centre for Nuclear Research PhD Student Seminar • "The Standard Model Extension, Gravitational tests and Cosmology and Cosmology Professor Comments of the Cosmology Professor Cosmology Prof	Prescott, USA January 25-31, 2020 Paris, France October 21-25, 2019 Prescott, USA April 3-18, 2019 B" Warsaw, Poland November 5, 2018 mology" Warsaw, Poland

Teaching Experience

• Teaching Assistant - Electrodynamics (PhD course), Autumn 2019

Review & Outreach Activity

- 2018-present: Reviewer activity. Papers reviewed: 7.
- 2015-2016: Supervised a group of high-school students in the building of a 3D printer.
- 2013: Involved in the outreach program "Her Teach Future" at Lund Institute of Technology, aimed at increasing the number of female students.

Non-Academic Experience

• ISIS Duty Technician Rutherford Appleton Laboratory

• Physics Science Technician Pimlico Academy

• Research Engineer - Radiation Safety MAX IV Laboratory

• Summer Student Diamond Light Source

• Tutor in Mathematics

Harwell, United Kingdom 2020 - present

London, United Kingdom 2015-2016

Lund, Sweden 2014-2015

Harwell, United Kingdom June-September 2013

> Helsingborg, Sweden January-June 2013

Language & IT

- Computers/IT
 - Windows, Ubuntu Linux & Debian Linux
 - MS Word & Excel
 - LATEX
 - Mathematica: xAct, Markov-Chain Monte Carlo cluster computations
 - Python: numpy, scipy, matplotlib, pandas, seaborn, skikit-learn, image processing
- Languages
 - Native level: Swedish, English. Average: French. Beginner: Polish level A1+